<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>

<chapter id="chapter.tubes">
 <title>Tubes</title>

 <para>
  Telepathy Tubes provide a user-to-user or user-to-group networking layer
  which applications can use to transfer data. Unlike a traditional
  peer-to-peer network, which requires IP addresses or a service discovery
  mechanism for locating peers, Telepathy Tubes provides contact-to-contact
  data transfer. Telepathy connection managers handle network traversal
  using the same technology as for file transfer and streamed media.
 </para>

 <para>
  Telepathy currently offers two data formats for Tubes.
  <interfacename>StreamTube</interfacename> channels allow for a regular
  network socket to be shared between clients. This is best when adapting
  existing applications or protocols to run over Telepathy Tubes.
  <interfacename>DBusTube</interfacename> channels allow for a D-Bus bus to
  be shared between clients. This enables the use of D-Bus method calling and
  signalling rather than requiring the developer to develop their own
  network protocol and should be strongly considered for new applications.
 </para>

 <para>
  Telepathy Tubes can either be one-to-one (between two users) or
  one-to-many (between a group of users).
 </para>

 <note>
  <title>An Example of Using Tubes in Your Application</title>

  <para>
   Alice wants Bob’s help in editing her report. In Alice’s word processor
   she chooses the option to collaboratively edit this document and she is
   shown a list of instant-messaging contacts who are enabled for Telepathy
   Tubes. She selects Bob's name from the list.
  </para>

  <para>
   The application requests an appropriate Tube channel from the Connection
   Manager. This channel is received and dispatched by Telepathy on Bob's
   computer. He is asked if he wishes to collaborate with Alice.
  </para>

  <para>
   Bob accepts the channel. The Telepathy Connection Managers set up the
   best data stream from the available options given the type of network and
   the communications protocol.
  </para>
 </note>

 <sect1 id="sect.tubes.compatibility">
  <title>Compatibility</title>

  <para>
   Support for Telepathy Tubes requires certain features in the connection
   manager and communications protocol, and thus cannot be supported by
   every connection manager. <xref linkend="table.tubes.compatibility"/>
   provides a list of known working connection managers.
  </para>

  <table id="table.tubes.compatibility">
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Connection Manager</entry>
      <entry>One-to-One Tubes</entry>
      <entry>One-to-Many Tubes</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>

    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Gabble</entry>
      <entry>Stream, D-Bus</entry>
      <entry>Stream, D-Bus</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Salut</entry>
      <entry></entry>
      <entry></entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <note>
   <title>XMPP Protocol Support</title>

   <para>
    Telepathy Tubes over XMPP uses a protocol extension has been documented
    <ulink url="http://telepathy.freedesktop.org/xmpp/tubes.html">on the
    Telepathy website</ulink>. It has not been submitted as a XEP.
   </para>
  </note>

 </sect1>

</chapter>
